Guide to the James Furman Papers MS 006
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
James Furman Papers
1963-1997
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
Furman, James, 1937-1989
MS 006
114
0.5 Linear Feet, 1 box
James Furman was born in Louisville, Kentucky in 1937 and was a college professor/Composer. The collection includes audio recordings of original material, performance programs, and biographical information.
Provenance
Transferred to Archives in 2002.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
James Furman was born in Louisville, Kentucky in 1937 and was a college professor/Composer. He studied piano and as a teenager won first place in the Louisville Philharmonic Society's Young Artist Contest in 1953. He received his Bachelor of Music Education and Master of Music in Theory-Composition degrees from the University of Louisville. He pursued graduate study at Brandeis and Harvard. In this time he studied under: Irving Fine, Arthur Berger, George Perle, Harold Shapero, Claude Almand, George Perle, Claude Almand, Irving Fine, Arthur Berger, and Harold Shapero.
He taught music in secondary schools in Louisville and Mamaroneck, and then at the College level at Western Connecticut State college in Danbury (1965-1989). His also composed choral works, songs, and chamber music. Some of his compositions of note include: "I Have a Dream" (1971), the trio "Variants" (1963), a choral suite "Four Little Foxes" (1965), and "Declaration of Independence" for orchestra and narrator (1977).
Sources:
Eileen Southerns Biographical Dictionary of Afro-American and African Musicians (Westport, Conn.: Greenwood Press, 1982).
James Furman [http://www.candlewood.net/furman/index.html]
Scope and Content Note
The collection includes audio recordings of original material, performance programs, and biographical information.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into 1 series:
Missing Title
Inventory
Phonograph records.; Correspondence.; Microfilm.; Fliers (printed matter); Louisville (Ky.); Polychoral music; Danbury (Conn.); Music Instruction and study.; Theater programs.; Audiotapes.; Western Connecticut State College.; Pegolotti, James A.
- Inventory, 38252
  - Biographical Information, undated; 38279 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Resumes and Opuses, 1990-1993; 38278 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence of James Pegolotti re Furman, undated; 38277 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Recollections of Furman, by Howard Tuvelle, 1997; 38276 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Concert Programs, 1966-1977; 38275 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Concert Programs, 1978-1984; 38274 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Concert Programs (Memorial Concert), 1989; 38273 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Estate of James Furman:Collection of Recordings, undated; 38272 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Estate of James Furman:Library, undated; 38271 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
  - Compositions:Ave Maria, undated; 38270 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Compositions:The Quiet Life, 1963; 38269 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Compositions:Variants, 1963; 38268 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - LP: Choir Festival 1967, sponsored by Danbury Chapter, American Guild of Organists, 38267 (Box 1, Item 1)
  - LP: Connecticut State Music Festival, Orchestra, Chorus, Band (2 lps ), 1982; 38266 (Box 1, Item 2)
  - LP: Music of America, 1750-1970, Greenwich Choral Society, 45th Anniversary (2 lps), Spring 1970, 38265 (Box 1, Item 3)
  - LP: Prelude No. 3 Andante from Rhapsody in Blue, undated; 38264 (Box 1, Item 4)
  - LP: Rolling Along of 1961, Army Special Services Presents... World-Touring Soldier Show Featuring Finalists from the 1961 All-Army Entertainment Contest (2 lp's), 38263 (Box 1, Item 5)
  - 78: Unidentified, label states "Mr. J. W. Hoppe,", undated; 38262 (Box 1, Item 6)
  - Audio Cassette, 1976-1981; 38261 (Box 1, Item 1)
    General note
    side: A: I Have a Dream, James Furman, 4/22/1976
    side: B: Intercollegiate Concert, Ives Hall, James Furman Introduction, 11/24/1981
  - Audio Cassette, undated; 38260 (Box 1, Item 2)
    side: A: Suite for Solo Clarinet, nd
    side: B: Songs from Proposed Musical (Songs from Mr. Pickwick, music by James Furman), nd
  - Audio Cassette, undated; 38259 (Box 1, Item 3)
    side: A: James Furman Works: Come Thou Long Expected Jesus, Four Little Foxes, Heylehlooyuh, I Have a Dream Hymn, WestConn Chorus, J. Furman directing, nd
    side: B: The Declaration of Independence, WCSU Orchestra, James Furman conducting, Ella Grasso narrating, nd
  - New American Choral Music - Vol. III - Music of Brian Fennelly, Ross Lee Finney, James Furman, Darrell Handel, Bain Murrary, Mel Powell, Robert Stern with the Gregg Smith Singer, Gregg Smith conducting, (Furman piece: Ave Maria & Salve Regina, Jupiter Shall Emerge), 1987; 38258 (Box 1, Item 4)
  - Audiotape - reel to reel: Analysis of Brandenburg Concerti, 1, 2, 3, undated; 38257 (Box 1, Item 5)
  - I Have a Dream - vocal score on microfilm: I Have a Dream, 1970; 38256 (Box 1, Reel 1-3)
    Microfilmed in 1970.
  - I Have a Dream - musical score on microfilm: I Have a Dream, 1970; 38255 (Box 1, Reel 4)
  - Pitch instrument "The Master Key, Chromatic Pitch Instrument, A-440, 13 Keys - A product of Wm. Kratt Co."Pitch instrument "The Master Key, Chromatic Pitch Instrument, A-440, 13 Keys - A product of Wm. Kratt Co.", undated; 38254 (Box 1, Item 1)
  - "Sir James Furman in Memoriam" compiled by Eric Lewis., 1989-1990; 38253 (Box 1, Item 2)
    3 ring binder which includes a variety of materials relating to Furman, his work and music. Items include: programs from the memorial service; lists of works; a description of Furman and the circumstances of his death written by Prof. Eric Lewis; clippings; correspondence relating to his estate; a note written by Furman; and sheet music. [ca. 75 pgs]